<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cry of oppression, occasioned by the priests of Englands pulpit-guard, which is a popish law that was made by Queen Mary, to guard her friars and Jesuits. With a true discovery of the unjust proceedings of those called magistrates of Bathe; wherein is a lamentation over them, and a warning unto them to repent, lest they perish for ever. / By one which is hatefully called a Quaker ... known to the world by the name, Thomas Morford.</title>
            <author>Morford, Thomas, d. 1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2728</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E989_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204878</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864332</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864332</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116559</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89302)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116559)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 147:E989[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cry of oppression, occasioned by the priests of Englands pulpit-guard, which is a popish law that was made by Queen Mary, to guard her friars and Jesuits. With a true discovery of the unjust proceedings of those called magistrates of Bathe; wherein is a lamentation over them, and a warning unto them to repent, lest they perish for ever. / By one which is hatefully called a Quaker ... known to the world by the name, Thomas Morford.</title>
                  <author>Morford, Thomas, d. 1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year. 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In 3 parts, with separate titlepages for parts 2 &amp; 3. Titlepage to part 2 (C4) reads: The deceit and enmity of the priests, manifested. Titlepage to part 3 (D4; caption title) reads: A testimony against the worlds feigned love, and salutations, and flattering titles. Pagination and register continuous throughout.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  England --  Bath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:116559:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE Cry of Oppreſsion, Occaſioned by the Prieſts of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Pulpit-guard, which is a Popiſh Law that was made by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> to guard her Friars and Jeſuits. With a true diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the unjuſt proceedings of thoſe called Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of <hi>Bathe;</hi> Wherein is a Lamentation over them, and a Warning unto them to repent, leſt they periſh for ever.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Iſa. 10.1, 2.</hi>
                        </bibl> Woe unto you that decree unrighteous decrees, and that write grievouſneſs, which they have preſcribed, to turn aſide the needy from judgement, and to take away the right from the poor of my people.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Iſa. 33.1.</hi>
                        </bibl> And when ye ſhall ceaſe to ſpoil, ye ſhall be ſpoiled, and when ye ſhall ceaſe to deal treacherouſly, they ſhall deal treacherouſly with you.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſalm 12.5.</hi>
                        </bibl> For now will I ariſe, ſaith the Lord, for the oppreſſing of the Poor, and for the ſighing of the needy, I will ſet him in ſafety from him that puffeth at him.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>By one which is hatefully called a <hi>QUAKER,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and perſecuted without a cauſe, a Priſoner for the Word of God, and teſtimony of Jeſus, he by whom the world was made, which ſaid, <hi>They ſhall hale you out of their Synagogues, and before Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and ſhall caſt you into priſon;</hi> and if they kill you (mark) <hi>they ſhall think they do God good ſervice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Known to the world by the Name, <hi>Thomas Morford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year. 1659.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:116559:2"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116559:2"/>
                  <head>THE CRY Of OPPRESSION: Occaſioned by the Prieſts of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Pulpit-guard, which is a Popiſh Law that was made by Queen <hi>MARY,</hi> to guard her Friars and Jeſuits. With a true diſcovery of the unjuſt proceedings of thoſe called Magiſtrates of <hi>Bathe;</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is a Lamentation over them, and a Warning unto them to Repent, leſt they periſh for ever.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the 27 day of the Third Month (called <hi>MAY</hi>) in the Year (according to the Worlds Account) 1655. I was moved of the living God to go into the Idol-Temple in the City of <hi>Bathe,</hi> and there was one Prieſt <hi>Sanger</hi> (Prieſt of <hi>Martins</hi> Pariſh, near the place called <hi>Charing Croſs</hi> in <hi>London,</hi>) ſtanding up praying in the high place, and as I ſtood by a chief ſeat, in that Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (or Synagogue) in which were two or three Prieſts, there came unto me he whom they call their Sexton, and ſaid, it was Prayer-time, and would have had me take off my hat, but I ſpake not a word unto him, yet heard I a voice ſaying unto me, <hi>The prayers of the wicked are abomination to the Lord.</hi> And the witneſs of God aroſe up in me very ſwift
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116559:3"/>againſt the falſe Prophet, (and againſt all the reſt of the falſe Prophets and Sorcerers that were there at that time from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places of the Land) that was ſpeaking lies in the Name of the Lord, ſaying, <hi>Hearken unto the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rd of the Lord,</hi> albeit the Lord ſpake not unto him, neither did the Lord ſend him: therefore did he not profit the people; and ſo dreadful and terrible was the power of the Living God on me, and in me, that I did exceedingly quake and tremble; his Word was in my boſome as a fire, I was weary with forbearing, I reeled like a drunken man, and was ready to ſink down to the ground, ſo heavy was the burthen and indignation of the Lord in me againſt the Sorcerers and falſe Prophets. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a little while the Lord by his ſecret power did ſtop the mouth of the falſe Prophet, which was ſpeaking lies in his Name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> before I had ſpoken the Word of the Lord: but then immediatly was I forced to roar out the burthen, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and indignation of the Lord againſt the Sorcerers and falſe Prophets, and the terrible day of the Lord, a day of bowling, howling that was (and is) coming upon them; then preſently they were in an uproar, and he (called their Sexton) with others fell upon me, haling and beating of me, that Chriſts words might be fulfilled, which ſaid, They ſhall beat you in their Synagogues, and hale you out of them, and hale you before Magiſtrates, and caſt you into priſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And another (as it was ſaid) cried out <hi>Stab him,</hi> hear the fruits of your Miniſtry.</p>
                  <p>Then came the Conſtables (that then were) of the Town, <hi>Robert Chapman,</hi> and <hi>Walter Gibbs,</hi> and haled me away pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to priſon: and as I was haling thither, the bruits that held me by my arms did ſtrive to break or wreſt them, but I was preſerved by the ſtrength and power of my God, out of their rage and madneſs; Praiſes to the Lord for ever.</p>
                  <p>On the next day I was brought before <hi>Iohn Biggs</hi> Mayor, that then was, and <hi>Matthew Cliff</hi> that then was called a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; they asked me, wherefore I came to diſturb their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter? I anſwered, the Lord ſent me (and truly ſo he did) to bear witneſs againſt him, for he was a deceiver, and a falſe Prophet, and hath deceived you; but they were not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116559:3"/>to diſpute the cauſe with me, but ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, except you give ſecurity to be of good behaviour, you muſt go to priſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; I demanded by what Law they judged me? they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, they had a Law: ſo I required to hear it, then they commanded their Clerk to read their Law to me, which was done; and that Law they read to me, and judged me by was a Law made by Queen <hi>Mary</hi> (which killed and Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſervants of God called Proteſtants in her daies) to guard her Friars and Jeſuits.</p>
                  <p>But had not thoſe that ſate as my Judges been wilfully blind and ignorant as well as malitious, but had had the leaſt meaſure of the wiſdom and ſpirit of God (which ought to be the only Guide and Counſellor of all faithful and juſt Judges, and Magiſtrates, which judge for the Lord in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and not for gifts and rewards,) truly they would have found a clauſe in that Law, whereby they might juſtly and truly have judged me guiltleſs of tranſgreſſing of that Popiſh Law it ſelf, for in that Law are theſe words, (that is to ſay) <hi>If any one ſhall wilfully, malitiouſly, and contemptuouſly &amp;c. let or diſturb any Preacher or Preachers, in his or their Sermon, &amp;c.</hi> that then they ſhould ſuffer according to that Law.</p>
                  <p>But the Lord that ſearcheth all hearts, and knows the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets and intents of all hearts, is my witneſs that I went not into that Temple or Synagogue at that time, by the wilful, malitious, contemptible will of man, but only in obedience to the movings and Spirit of the living God, which movings are contrary to the will of man (he that hath an an ear to hear, can hear and underſtand) yet ſo contrary to the true ſenſe of the Law, I was had to priſon again.</p>
                  <p>Now let the light of Chriſt in all judge what ground the Prieſts ſtand upon, and have for their Miniſtry, that are not able to ſtand or defend themſelves without a Popiſh Law to guard them; neither they nor any elſe can deny it, for it was read to me, and by it have I been wrongfully kept in priſon, and by thoſe that were the Miniſters of it, above nineteen months; but I denied to be judged by that Law, for I told them it was a Popiſh law, made by that wicked Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> which killed the ſervants of the Lord; but they anſwered,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116559:4"/>they could not help it, for it was not repealed.</p>
                  <p>Now if it be not repealed, let all the wiſe in God judge by what followeth, by a Law of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (touching Common-prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Act 10. Chap. 2. laſt Clauſe, its ſaid, <hi>That all Laws, Statutes, Ordinances, &amp;c. wherein or whereby any other ſervices, Adminiſtrations, Sacraments, or Common-Prayers are licenſed, or ſet forth to be uſed, ſhall be from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth utterly void, and of none effect.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if you ſay it is not repealed by the Statute aforeſaid, yet prove I it void, from that firſt Principle of the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in the Book <hi>(Doct. &amp; Student.)</hi> Chap. 2. to this effect: <hi>That the Law of God is the only true ground of all Laws; and that all Laws, Statutes, Ordinances, Cuſtoms, or Preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whatſoever, that are contrary to the righteous Law of God, are all null, void, and of none effect, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And alſo in OLIVER the Protectors Articles of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Article 35. are theſe words, <hi>viz. That the Chriſtian Religion contained in the Scripture be held forth, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the publick profeſſion of the Nation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Article 37. <hi>That ſuch as profeſs Faith in God, by Jeſus Chriſt, though differing in judgement from the Doctrine, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Diſcipline publickly held forth, ſhall not be reſtrained from, but ſhall be protected in the profeſſion of the Faith, and exerciſe of their Religion: ſo that they abuſe not this Liberty to the civil injury of others, and to the actual diſturbance of the publick peace on their part,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Article 38. <hi>That all Laws, Statutes, Ordinances, and Clauſes in any Law, Statute, or Ordinance to the contrary of the aforeſaid Liberty, ſhall be eſteemed as null and void.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now this is according to the Law of God, and to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, and is contained in the holy Scriptures of truth, to go into a Synagogue, or Steeple-houſe, and there to ask a queſtion, or to diſpute, or to bear witneſs againſt the falſe worſhips; it being the manner of Chriſt, and his holy Prophets and Apoſtles ſo to do, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.2. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.46. And it was and is the order in the holy Church of Chriſt, as the Scriptures teſtifie, to wit, <hi>That if any thing be revealed to him that ſtands by, let the firſt hold his peace, for ye may all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116559:4"/>propheſie one by one,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14.29, 30. and therefore it being according to the Law of God, and to Chriſtian Religion, and the Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, profeſſed and exerciſed by the Lord Jeſus, and his Miniſters, and being no civil injury to any, nor diſturbance to the publick peace on my part, to go and bear witneſs againſt a falſe worſhip, and hireling Prieſt, I ought to be protected therein, as in the exerciſe of the true Chriſtian Religion.</p>
                  <p>And therefore (undoubtedly) your ſaid Popiſh Law is repealed, void, and of none effect, as I have proved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                  <p>And therefore ye Rulers of <hi>Bathe</hi> have unjuſtly (like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable men) kept me a priſoner above theſe nineteen months, and have not convicted me of the tranſgreſſion of the righteous Law of God, (which ought to be your Rule, <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.17, 18, 19) or any Law of the Nation.</p>
                  <p>As I was informed, ſome of you (called Magiſtrates) ſaid, if ye ſhould let me go without giving you Bonds of Security for good behaviour, (as ye call it) that I would ſue you at your Law for wrong impriſonment; <hi>Vengeance is mine,</hi> ſaith the Lord, who is come and coming to give to you, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as your Works ſhall be; and to him do I commit my cauſe, who will in his righteous judgements eaſe him of his adverſaries, and avenge him of his enemies. The light of Chriſt in your conſciences will be your Judge and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which condemnation will be forer torment unto you than the loſs of all your outward riches, or glory, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judgement that man can inflict upon your carnal bodies; ſo your fear and jealouſie I do deny; and your evill I do not reſiſt, but in patience do ſuffer your wrong, till he for whoſe teſtimony I ſuffer, work away for my deliverance, out of the hands of unreaſonable men. And in a few dayes after my firſt committing to priſon, <hi>John Biggs</hi> that then was (called) Mayor, ſent <hi>William Baker</hi> his Serjeant, with this Meſſage (as he ſaid) if I would ſay I was ſorry, and to that effect, for what I had done, he would ſet me at liberty; to which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that I was ſo far from being ſorry for the teſtimony that I had borne againſt the Prieſts, that I would ſeal it with my blood, if it were required; and to this my anſwer, the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116559:5"/>Keeper of the priſon that then was, (which ſince hath left the priſon) was witneſs: yet notwithſtanding <hi>William Baker</hi> went and told his Maſter the Mayor, that I ſaid that if I were out of priſon I would go and do the like again, which was falſe, and the Keeper of the priſon did witneſs ſo to <hi>William Bakers</hi> face; for which <hi>William Baker</hi> gave him very uncivil language, and for that cauſe a little while after <hi>John Biggs</hi> would not ſuffer my Friends that came to viſit me, to come at me, while he was in his power, but commanded the Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to keep me in the inner priſon, yet <hi>William Baker</hi> gave me to my face very fair words, and did witneſs that what I then ſaid to him was truth; the Lord lay not this ſin to thy charge <hi>William Baker,</hi> for thou didſt falſly accuſe me at that time, the light of Chriſt in thy Conſcience is my witneſs, but it was that the Scripture might be fulfilled, which ſaith, <hi>That in the laſt dayes men ſhall be traytors, heady, high-minded, proud, covetous, boaſters, blaſphemers, fierce, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good,</hi> and (mark) <hi>falſe accuſers, &amp;c.</hi> 2 Tim. 3.1, 2.</p>
                  <p>And on the fifth day of the Ninth month, 1655. (that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the day of their Seſſions) the Rulers of <hi>Bathe</hi> ſent for me to their Seſſions before them; and when I came into their Court. <hi>John Boyce</hi> that then was (called) Mayor, asked me, if I knew before whom I ſtood (for he with others of them were clothed in Scarlet, and Velvet, but the end will be woe) I anſwered I did, ſo he commanded to take off my hat, and it was done, and one of them gave it me in my hand, and I put it on my head again: <hi>Edward Parker</hi> one of their Bayliffs or Sheriffs that then was ſtanding by me, (being filled with rage and madneſs, as well as Wine or ſtrong Drink) haled my hat off my head again, and ſtruck me in the face; I asked them (if they) ſat to judge me according to Law, and contrary to Law, did ſuffer me to be ſtruck in their Court, and ſaid, God will judge and ſmite you; but there was ſuch a rude noiſe amongſt them, that they could ſcarce hear or underſtand what each other ſaid, for their carriage was more like Dogs barking, and Swine renting, than like men that ſate to judge the cauſe of the Oppreſſed, and Afflicted, ſuch was the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of ſome of thoſe Which ſat as Judges, and Juſtices; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116559:5"/>would they (ſcarce) ſuffer him; they called their May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or that then was to ſpeak, which I ſuppoſe would have done Juſtice, had he not feared the ill-will of his Brethren; and ſo I reproved them for their rudeneſs, and ſaid, if they ſtood before a Magiſtrate of God, who judged righteouſly for the Lord, they would dread and tremble at his preſence, for the eyes of a faithful King, Judge, or Magiſtrate (who hateth Gifts and Rewards, which judgeth without partiality, and wreſteth not the cauſe of the poor, nor reſpecteth the perſon of the Rich) ſcattereth the Wicked, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.8, 26. but at laſt the Mayor had leave to ſpeak, and ſaid unto me, except I did give ſecurity to be of good behaviour, that I muſt go to priſon again, ſo commanded to take me away, and charged the Keeper to keep me up in the inner priſon, and not to ſuffer any to come at me but my Wife, whoſe outward dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling was three miles from the Town; yet he did not deny any Friend (that came to viſit me) if they asked him to come at me; and <hi>John Parker</hi> called an Alderman, cryed out, throw him into the Dungeon, and put bolts of iron upon him; ſo they haled me to priſon again, and did not at all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince me of any Law I had tranſgreſſed; and committed my Friend <hi>T. H.</hi> that was with me to priſon alſo, that gave them no juſt offence in word or action, but only ſtood there pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceably to ſee if I might have juſtice; but after they were a little cool (for many of them were much inflamed with Wine and ſtrong Drink, which did not become men of their places, <hi>Prov:</hi> 31.4, 5.) they releaſed my Friend out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon again.</p>
                  <p>And upon the 23 day of the Fourth month, 1656. came ſome Friends of <hi>Briſtol</hi> into <hi>Bathe,</hi> and one of them went to <hi>John Boyce</hi> the Mayor that then was, and ſpake ſomething unto him concerning his keeping me in priſon, and at that time there was with the Mayor the Conſtable of <hi>Bathe</hi> that then was, <hi>Henry Parker,</hi> and they had had ſome diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my releaſing out of priſon; ſo the Conſtable did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage (as did after appear) for my good behaviour, and that I ſhould not commit the like offence; ſo the Mayor bad him go and fetch me forth of priſon: ſo he came up to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and that Friend with him, and asked me whether I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116559:6"/>was willing to go forth of priſon, and ſaid, the Mayor had ſent him to releaſe me, but he did not tell me plainly that he had engaged for me as aforeſaid, but was very urgent (and ſo was that Friend alſo that came with him, that I think did not know their deceit) to have me go with him; but I gave them little anſwer, but waited to know the mind of the Lord, (for the Lord had afore-ſhewed unto me, that ſo they ſhould come and fetch me forth, and bad me not hearken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and alſo ſent his Meſſenger upon the 27. day of the Third month, 1656. which was but little before the Conſtable came to me, and he ſaid unto me, take heed how thou do come forth, leſt thou art enſnared, but come forth freely, or elſe thou wilt rue it the longeſt day thou liveſt; ſo having a command from the infallible Spirit of the living God not to hearken unto them, and fore-warned by his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger without, I was in great dread and fear, and was not haſty to anſwer them a word; upon which the Conſtable was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly urgent upon me for an anſwer, pretending much feigned love, and uſing many words unto me, and ſaid, The Lord in times paſt did give his ſervants a tongue to ſpeak, and immediatly did reveal in them what to ſay, and asked me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, whether I was not willing to go forth of priſon? to which I anſwered, that this is that the Lord hath immediatly revealed in me, I am willing in his time to go forth of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but ye have kept me here near fourteen months a priſoner to ſatisfie your luſts and envy, and have not ſo much as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed me of the tranſgreſſion of any juſt Law of this Nation; neither have ye had me to your Seſſions theſe two or three Seſſions, which ye ought to have done, and there to have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted judgement upon me if I had deſerved it, and been convicted of the tranſgreſſion of any juſt Law; but your carriage the laſt time I was there was ſuch unto me, I think it hath cauſed ſhame as well as hardneſs of heart to poſſeſs ſome of you, or elſe there to have cleared me, which is according to the Law of the Nation, which is not denyed to Felons and murtherers, which if ye do refuſe to do, let them that ſent me to priſon come and fetch me forth. To this effect, if not the very words was my anſwer to the Conſtable: at which he was much diſcontented, and ſaid, I was a falſe Prophet, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116559:6"/>Deceiver, or worſe to that purpoſe, and ſaid, I might lye in priſon till Doomſ-day (as he called it) before they that ſent me to priſon would fetch me forth, and ſo he departed; then it was preſently reported that I might come forth of priſon, but that I loved to lye in priſon, or to that effect; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon there being ſome Friends in Town at that time, they ſent the ſaid Friend that came to me, with the Conſtable, to the Mayor again, (by reaſon he ſaid as well as others, I might come forth of priſon, but I would not) to fetch a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge for the Keeper of the priſon, it being according to the Law of the Nation ſo to do; ſo that Friend being urgent upon the Mayor for a Diſcharge, he did write (inſtead of a Diſcharge) a charge to the Keeper for to keep my body in priſon, and called for an Officer to carry it to the Keeper, but looking again upon that Friend that went for a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, he ſaid, I think thou art pretty honeſt, give it to the Keeper. This following is a Copy of it; let the wiſe in God judge.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="writ">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>George Mittins,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>YOu are deſired to keep the body of Mr.</hi> MORFORD <hi>Priſoner, till he give ſecurity for his good abeiſance. No more at preſent,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Yours, <hi>J. B.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>So when thoſe Friends ſaw that charge to keep me in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, inſtead of a diſcharge, they went down to the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, and told him of it; to which he ſaid, that they had no intent to let me forth, but to try whether I would go forthor not, which will be proved if it be required, and to two of thoſe Friends whoſe Names are here ſubſcribed, he ſaid that he had engaged to the Mayor, that <hi>Thomas Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> ſhould not commit the like offence, if he would ſet him at liberty; then the Conſtable being demanded whether I might come forth of priſon without any pretended ſecurity from any man by word or deed; he anſwered, I might not. To this teſtimony the ſaid Friends have ſubſcribed their Names, <hi>Charles Jones, John Wathen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:116559:7"/>
                  <p>And on the next day came ſome Friends from <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and thereabouts to <hi>Bathe</hi> for to viſit me in the priſon; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they came unto me, ſome of them went to the Mayor, and ſpake ſomething to him concerning my long, fore, and unjuſt impriſonment; ſo he told them that he would have ſet me at liberty the yeſterday, but I did refuſe to go forth, and ſaid unto them, tell his Friends of <hi>Briſtol</hi> of it; then thoſe Friends (when they came to priſon to me) told me what the Mayor had ſaid unto them; then I ſhewed them the true cauſe why I did not go forth, and the Mayors Charge inſtead of a Diſcharge. Then ſome of them went down to him again, and ſhewed him his deceit: then he was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing angry with them, and called for an Officer to ſend them to priſon, but after his paſſion was a little over, he told them the Seſsions was very near, and then he would ſend for me to the Seſsions; then thoſe Friends urged him again to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his promiſe: he bad them not fear, for it ſhould be ſo.</p>
                  <p>Upon the 14. day of the Fifth Month, 1656. (it being the day of their Quarter. Seſsions) thoſe Friends came again to <hi>Bathe,</hi> and ſome of them went down to the Mayors houſe that morning, before he went to the Seſsions, to mind him of his promiſe that he had made them: but he was very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with them, and bad them go out of his houſe, and come to the Hall a thouſand of them, and he would anſwer them, ſo they (though not a thouſand of them) did go to the Hall, where as ſoon as they appeared before them called Juſtices, which ſhould have done juſtice, ſome of them which ware long Robes, with ſome others, fell upon my Friends, haling and pulling of them like wild Bruits, and thruſting them down ſtairs, ready to ſpoil their bodies; and ſo though <hi>John Boyce</hi> that then was called Mayor bad them come to the Hall he ſuffered them to be ſo abuſed; then they waited below till they were going to dinner, and then they charged the Mayor with his promiſe again: then he told them in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon he would ſend for me to the Seſsions; in the afternoon they went again, and required him to perform his promiſe, and to do juſtice; but he that was called the Recorder, <hi>James Aſh,</hi> paſſed away, and did not do me juſtice: neither
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116559:7"/>did the Mayor (notwithſtanding all his promiſes) ſend for me to the Seſsions; but a little before they left the Hall that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the Rulers ſent up <hi>Carew Davis</hi> their Serjeant unto me in the priſon, to know if I had any ſecurity; to which I anſwered, if they would let me go down to their Hall, and there convince me as a Tranſgreſſor of any juſt Law, I was willing to receive any Puniſhment that might be inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me according to that Law; and there was a Friend, a rich man in the outward, offered ſecurity if they proved me a Tranſgreſſor, or of any evill behaviour; ſo the Sergeant went down, and ſome of my Friends with him to them again, and gave them my anſwer, and my Friends that offered ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and their anſwer was, except my Friends did engage to be my ſecurity, before I did come out of priſon, I ſhould not come forth. We are witneſſes to the truth hereof, whoſe Names are here ſubſcribed.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Johns,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Weare,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Anne Hill,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Eliz. Atwood,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Iones,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Terret,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Katherine Evans,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Wickham,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Anth. Sturbs,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioan Screen.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Upon the 25 day of the Sixth month, 1656. came the Keeper of the priſon unto me, and ſaid, I might go forth of priſon if I would, I demanded of him who did give ſuch order? then he ſeemed to be very angry with me for queſtioning of him, and would give me none other account; I told him if they did put beggars in priſon but a night or two, they did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſend for them before their Magiſtrates, and there clear them, and have they kept me here almoſt ſixteen months un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly, and now think to thruſt me out privately, with thy ſaying, I may go out of priſon if I will, ſo he paſſed away from me, and I waited to know from the Lord what I ſhould do. So after a little while I was moved of the Lord to write a Letter to the Mayor, which was in ſubſtance accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to what is before declared, and therefore ſhall omit it here; and to know of him the certainty of the Keepers ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that I might go forth of priſon if I would, and I ſent it down by my Wife, ſo the Mayor bad my Wife bring a man
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116559:8"/>of the Town to him, and ſhe ſhould know more of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo at that very inſtant there came a Friend of <hi>Briſtol</hi> to priſon to me, and I deſired him to go down to the Mayor, and to know what his intent was towards me: ſo he did, where, as ſoon as he appeared, the Mayor came and took him by the hand, and asked him what Country-man he was, which being anſwered, he took him aſide, and ſaid, we are about to ſet <hi>Thomas Morford</hi> at liberty, and this is all we will require of you, that is to ſay, that you will promiſe that when he is forth he ſhall be civil, and of good behaviour, and (ſaid the Mayor) we will put him forth, and he ſhall never know you promiſed any ſuch thing: which my Friend deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (knowing that I was innocent, and had not been of any evill behaviour, neither had deſerved any part of that unjuſt impriſonment, the Mayor began to be angry, and ſaid that every ſoul ought to be ſubject to the Higher Powers; To which my Friend anſwered by way of Queſtion; Art thou that higher power to which the Soul of Man ought to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject? To which the Mayors anſwer was, if he thou'd him, he would bind him to the good Behaviour, and bad him be gone about his buſineſs; and that Friend to teſtifie the truth concerning the Keepers ſaying, I might go forth of priſon if I would, hath ſubſcribed his Name, which is <hi>Iohn Weale</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon the 11. day of the Ninth Month 1656. (that being the day of their Quarter-Seſſions) <hi>Matthew Cliffe</hi> at this time called Mayor, Ordered at the Seſsions (but thither he did not ſend for me, but judged me before he tryed me, and there ſlaundered me with falſe accuſations behind my back, and ſaid I was a Railer, and a Diſturber, as it was ſaid, and charged the Keeper to keep me in the inner priſon, and not to ſuffer any to come at me, but my Wife; in which inner pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon being a cloſe dark room, they have kept me the greateſt part of theſe nineteen months, into which ſometimes in rainy weather runs down ſtreams of water, then which the Law of the Nation affords better for Felons and Murtherers. And there was a Felon (with another) put over the room where I was, and the Felon brake through the ſealing over-head in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the room where I was: &amp; becauſe <hi>I</hi> gave notice to the Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116559:8"/>and did not give my conſent for him to break the reſt of the priſon, when he was put up again, he threw down his piſs or Urine ſeveral times over the place where my bed was, that it might run down upon it.</p>
                  <p>Upon the 17 day of the ſaid Ninth Month came <hi>Anne Blacklin,</hi> and ſeveral other Friends with her to viſit me, and deſired the Keeper that they might come into priſon to me; but his anſwer was that the Mayor had commanded not to ſuffer any to come in except my Wife; ſo <hi>Anne Blacklin</hi> and thoſe other Friends went to <hi>Matthew Cliffe</hi> the (called) Mayor, and deſired him that they might be permitted to come into the priſon to me, but he told her ſhe ſhould not come in to me, nor ſee my face, for he ſaid, I had abuſed their Miniſter, and was a Railer: then ſhe bad him ſend for me before his face, and convince me of evill, or being a Rayler, but that he refuſed to do, and ſaid he would ſend for me the next Seſſions, and then if I did not what he did require of me, he would ſend me to <hi>Bridewel,</hi> and ſo he rudely and unbecoming a Magiſtrate, to ſo evill entreat a ſtranger, and give ſuch an evill example, thruſt her and her Friends out of his houſe, and would not ſuffer them to come into priſon to me, though ſhe told him ſhe came a purpoſe from <hi>Briſtol</hi> to viſit me; and in a few dayes after came <hi>Iames Travers,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Wickham</hi> to <hi>Bathe,</hi> and deſired the Keeper to let them into the priſon to me, but the Keeper or his Wife told <hi>Iohn Wickham</hi> that the Mayor had charged them not to let in any, but my Wife, for if they did, he would take away the keyes from them; and <hi>Iames Stirredge,</hi> and <hi>Iames Travers</hi> went to <hi>Matthew Cliffe</hi> Mayor, to know of him what Law he had to keep me ſo cloſe priſoner; he told them he had a Law, but ſhewed them none, and would not ſuffer them to come into priſon, neither would he give leave to any that ever asked him (to come in to viſit me) to come in.</p>
                  <p>And whereas thou <hi>Matthew Cliffe,</hi> and ye <hi>Iohn Boyce,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Biggs</hi> who were Mayors before him, with others of your company, do accuſe me for Railing, Railing I do deny, and do not uſe (or bring) railing accuſations againſt any man, and ſo that ſlander I do return back again on your own heads, who are the falſe Accuſers, and in the nature of Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116559:9"/>Did I rail at thee <hi>Iohn Boyce,</hi> and thee <hi>Matthew Cliff,</hi> and the reſt of your company on the 5. day of the Ninth month 1655. when ye paſſed in pride and pomp, with your pipes ſounding before you through the gate to <hi>Thomas Scrines</hi> houſe to feaſt, where ye feaſted and enflamed your ſelves with Wine and ſtrong Drink, without the fear of the Lord? I ſay unto you, Did I rail, to tell you, as it was it was in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> ſo ſhall it be, and is in this the day of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Son of Man: <hi>They eat</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>they drank, &amp;c.</hi> &amp; bid you repent (with a lamentation over you) &amp; mind the light of Chriſt in you, which ſhewed you ſin and evill, and reproved you for it, for that was your Teacher, for your Teachers without you have deceived you, and I ſaid (and now affirm again) that the Lord will ſtain your pride and glory; and this I was moved of the living God to ſpeak unto you, for which ye cauſed me to be ſhut into the inner priſon, before ye came back, and uſed me ſo uncivil and brutiſh that night, at your Seſsions as I ſaid before.</p>
                  <p>And did I rail at thee <hi>Matthew Cliffe,</hi> the 9. day of the Ninth Month 1655. becauſe I asked thee as thou paſſedſt through the gate, when thou wouldſt fear the living God, and do Juſtice? Or did I rail at thee the 16. day of that month, I being moved of the Lord to go out into the outward pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (the inner priſon door being but a very little while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore left open) which I believe was the mind of the Lord ſo to have it, and immediatly thou paſſedſt by with thy Mace before thee, to the Idol Temple; and the Word of the Lord came unto me ſaying, ſay unto <hi>Matthew Cliffe,</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord God of hoſts, Except thou repent, and meet me the living God by Repentance, I will cut thy life off from the earth, and thou ſhalt go down to thy Grave in ſorrow; and when thou art on thy bed of Torment, remember how thou ſleightedſt the day of thy Viſitation; and this was the Word of the Lord unto thee, The light of Chriſt in thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and in all your Conſciences, ſhall eternally witneſs me to be true; and this was the ſubſtance of whatever I ſpake to any of you as aforeſaid, which for the clearing of Truth, and my Innocency, and taking off of your reproach, I was preſſed in my ſpirit to ſend forth this as a teſtimony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116559:9"/>you, for it is no more than what is contained in the holy Scripture of truth; and let the wiſe in God judge. And I ſay unto you, (as <hi>Eliah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ahab</hi>) who are in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, from the greateſt Prince, to the leaſt of you all, that ye are they that diſturb and trouble the Nations, in that ye do not keep the peace which ye ought to do, but ſuffer the Lords ſervants (whom he hath ſent unto you) to preach his everlaſting Goſpel freely, and to fore warn you of his great and mighty day that is come, and coming upon you all, and of his great wrath, and fierce indignation that he will aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly pour forth upon you except you ſpeedily repent, to be beaten with ſticks, and ſtones, dirted, whipped, ſtocked, and to be caſt into priſon, and there to periſh by long and ſore unjuſt impriſonment; and ye are thoſe that have itching ears, heaping up to your ſelves Teachers, to wit, your hireling Prieſts, which propheſie falſely, and divine for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and ſpeak peace to the wicked, which put into their mouths, and againſt them that do not, they prepare war. And ſo ye are thoſe that do hold up the horrible filthy thing in the Land, and cannot endure ſound Doctrine, but are making havock of the ſervants of the moſt high God; and ye do plainly manifeſt your ſelves to be ſuch Princes as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> called <hi>Ravening Wolves,</hi> which made it their prey to ſhed blood, <hi>&amp;c. Ezek.</hi> 22.27. And to tell you plainly from the Spirit of the living God, what ye are, is no railing: but the day will come, ye will confeſs it to be more honeſty and faithfulneſs in them that ſo do from the Spirit of the Lord, than it is in them that preach peace to the Wicked.</p>
                  <p>So my grievous and unjuſt oppreſſions I have received from theſe unreaſonable men, I leave to the Lord, and all that fear his Name to judge thereof.</p>
                  <p>Oh! all ye Inhabitants of the Earth, the dreadfull and mighty day of the Lord is come, and coming upon you all unawares, as a Theefe in the night, and though ye are ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, peace, and ſafety, ſudden and eternal deſtruction as a whirlwind will come upon you, except ye repent; and in particular upon you, O ye Inhabitants of <hi>Bathe,</hi> who are a ſhelter for all wickedneſs, pride, and wantonneſs, fulneſs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116559:10"/>of Bread, and all uncleanneſs abound amongſt you; ye are ſeen as <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> the Lord will ſtain your pride and glory, and the righteous judgements of the Lord will be heavy upon you: your bleſsings which ye have turned into laſciviouſneſs, luſts, and uncleanneſs, are corrupted and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, and the day haſteneth that all that fear the living God, will not ſeek unto them, but our waters ſhall be a wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing place for Swine, and the wild Beaſts of the field, and the Sword of the Lord will be upon the arm, and the right eye of your Idol Shepheards, and falſe prophets, <hi>Zack.</hi> 11.17. Their right eye will utterly be darkened, and their arm clean dryed up, and ſome of you ſhall wander up and down with your earthen veſſels to ſeek water, and this is the plague the Lord will ſmite you with, who are perſecutors of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed ones;
<note place="margin">Amos 8.12.</note> Your fleſh ſhall conſume away while ye ſtand upon your feet, your eyes ſhall conſume in their holes, and your tongues conſume away in your mouths,
<note place="margin">Zack. 14.12.</note> nothing of this ſhall fail, the mouth of the Lord of Hoſts hath ſpoken it; at a time appointed it will ſpeak, and not lye; and if in the day of the Lord they ſhall be caſt into everlaſting fire, that did not viſit the leaſt of Chriſts little-ones in priſon; What ſhall ye do that caſt them in, and will not ſuffer them that do come to viſit them to come at them. Witneſs to this againſt thee <hi>Matthew Cliffe, Anne Blacklin,</hi> &amp;c. whoſe teſtimonies will ſtand againſt thee for ever; and alſo againſt thee <hi>Iohn Bigg,</hi> ſhall witneſs <hi>Nicholus Jordan, Iohn Dowel, Nathaniel Milner,</hi> and <hi>Sara Bennet</hi> of <hi>Briſtol</hi> (in the year 1655.) with ſeveral others; for at that time the ſaid <hi>N. Iordan</hi> coming up the ſtreet of <hi>Bathe</hi> a little after his Wife, and my other Friends, there came two young men (<hi>Samuel Whitehead,</hi> and <hi>George Sprat</hi>) with a cord, and interwinding <hi>N. Iordan</hi> in the cord, ſtruck up his heels, and he fell upon the hard ſtones, ready to break his bones, he being (at that time) but a weak man in body; and when he appealed to thee <hi>Iohn Bigg,</hi> no redreſs he had: ſo thou didſt plainly manifeſt thy ſelf to bear the Sword in vain, who letteſt the evill-doer go free.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:116559:10"/>
                  <p>Upon the 26. day of the Fourth month (called <hi>Iune</hi>) laſt paſt, there being the ſervants of the Lord met together (in the hired houſe and ground of <hi>Thomas Dyer</hi>) and as they were peaceably and quietly waiting and hearing the Word of the Lord from his ſervants, <hi>Tho. Salthouſe, Miles Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> the bruit people gathered about the place where they were, hallowing and yawling, like wild Beaſts, throwing ſtones and dirt, as though they would have murthered the peaceable people of the Lord, and ſorely hurt <hi>Tho. Salthouſe</hi> in the head with a ſtone, while he was ſpeaking the Word of the Lord freely, in love to their Souls; and when thoſe Friends paſſed away from the Meeting, the brutiſh people followed them in the ſtreet, throwing ſtones and dirt at them as though they had been wild mad, whooping, and yawling, and beating of a Drum; and this is the fruits of your Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and yet ye ſay to us, Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher power; and a little before ye Rulers of <hi>Bathe</hi> caſt me into priſon, I was paſſing peaceably with two of my Friends. <hi>T. H.</hi> and <hi>R. S.</hi> down your ſtreets, none of us gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any offence in word or action; at that time a multitude of your brutiſh people fell upon us, and were like to murther us, we being all at that time exceeding weak in our bodies; and thou <hi>Robert Allen</hi> (who art above forty years of Age) thou ſhouldeſt have had more wit and reaſon, than to have given ſuch an evill example to the younger, as thou didſt in beating me; the Lord forgive Thee, and not lay it to thy charge.</p>
                  <p>And I have been very ſick in your priſon, ſo that my very fleſh conſumed away, and my bones were corrupted, and ye viſited me not; and when I have been hungry, thoſe whom the Lord had ſent to bring me meat, ye have ſeveraltimes been ready to murther them, which was my Wife, <hi>Iohn Evans</hi> her Brother, and his Wife and Daughter, and <hi>Tho. Hawkins,</hi> one of them was once ſore wounded; and the Bruits being asked why they did ſo? they anſwered, that <hi>Iohn Bigg</hi> the Mayor that then was, bad them beat my Friends out of Town, becauſe they were <hi>Quakers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe unjuſt actions will light heavy on you which are called Juſtices, and Magiſtrates, who ought to be a terror
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116559:11"/>to ſuch evill-doers, and keepers of the peace, and protectors of the Innocent, for elſe ye bear the Sword in vain, and the Sword of the Lord will be turned againſt you, who is the Higher Power, and unto him your Souls ought to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
                  <p>And ye that are Rulers of Families, ought to be examples in Righteouſneſs, Moderation, and Meekneſs of Life to your Servants, and Children, and to admoniſh and nurture them up in the fear of the Lord, and to correct them for abuſing and mocking ſuch as do neither you nor them any harm; But (O ye Inhabitants of <hi>Bathe</hi>) what evill examples do ye give one to another, both Magiſtrates, Prieſts, and People, in Swearing, Lying, Drunkenneſs, buying one another at Law, and living in all manner of uncleanneſs, your Children run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning up and down ſtreets whooping, and yawling, like wild Bruits, mocking and abuſing ſtrangers, which doth teſtifie what breeding and manners their Parents have brought them up in, which neither fear God, nor regard man, and yet ſome of them are (called) Centlemens Children; but they are but Gentiles Children which know not God, for ſurely were there either Parents, Magiſtrates, or Miniſters that did truly fear the living God, their Children would bring forth ſome better Fruits: but it is like Prieſts, like People. Oh that ye Perſecutors of the Lords people knew the thing that belongs to your peace before it be held from your eyes, and your hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes left deſolate, and that thing is Chriſt Jeſus the light of the world, in which did ye believe in truth, and follow, it would lead you into the good manners, and out of the evill communication, and lead you to live a righteous holy life, without which none ſhall ſee the Lord, and to do unto all men, as ye would that they ſhould do unto you, and that is good Religion.</p>
                  <p>Oh that ye knew the day of your Viſitation, and that there were hearts in you truly to fear the Lord, and that ye rightly conſidered of your latter-end, before that day of wrath come upon you, wherein your Souls will have no pleaſure, which is reſerved for the Wicked, Perditions, and ungodly ones; then ye ſhall confeſs him which now ye call a natural light, to be ſupernatural, when he will fit in your Conſcience as a Refiners
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116559:11"/>fire, and as an Oven that burneth, when your breath as a fire is conſuming you, being kindled by the Spirit of burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and of judgement from the Lord God; but did ye love and follow the light which Chriſt hath enlightened you withall, it would lead you out of that great indignation which will aſſuredly come upon you, except ye do repent. But if ye do rebelliouſly reject the day of your viſitation, and ſalvation proffered unto you; remember when ye are in the pit ye were fore-warned of it; and this is love to your Souls, and I do beſeech the Lord to forgive this great evill ye have done againſt me, who am the leaſt of his ſervants. Lord lay it not to their charge, for they know not what they have done.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>To the light of Chriſt in all your Conſciences I ſpeak, which ſhall eternally witneſs me to be true, and anſwer your Condemnation to be juſt, if ye rebell againſt the light. T. M.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:116559:12"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:116559:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE DECEIT AND ENMITY OF THE <hi>PRIESTS,</hi> Manifeſted.</p>
                  <p>And the Doctrine of <hi>PERFECTION</hi> (by them denyed as Popiſh) witneſſed by the Scriptures to be the Doctrine of Chriſt, his Prophets, and Miniſters. And the <hi>POPE</hi> with his Prieſts, and Friars, and the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> proved to differ nothing in ground and nature one from the other.</p>
                  <p>WHEREIN, Is alſo an Exhortation to all People to Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine themſelves whether they have the true Faith, and Hope, and Belief, with their Effects and Operations as they are in Jeſus.</p>
                  <p>LIKEWISE, XX. QUERIES Propounded to <hi>George Long,</hi> High Prieſt of <hi>Bathe,</hi> and Prieſt <hi>Sangers</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> by them to be anſwered in Print, or Writing.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Hoſ. 6 8.</hi>
                        </bibl> As troops of robbers watch for a man, ſo the company of Prieſts murther in the way by conſent.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And Chriſt ſaid,</hi> Falſe Prophets, and falſe Chriſts ſhall arîſe, ye ſhall know them by their fruits: they ſhall cry, Lo here, and lo there, believe them not, nor go not forth, for the kingdom of God is within you. And, Chriſt is in you except you be reprobates.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1659.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:116559:13"/>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116559:13"/>
                  <head>THE Deceit and Enmity OF THE PRIESTS MANIFESTED.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E Prieſts, oppreſſion, and injuſtice are the fruits of your Miniſtry: the controverſie of the Lord is great againſt you, and of you will the Lord require all the Souls that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh under your Miniſtry, for ye have only ſought your own gain, and eaſe, and have not ſought that which hath been loſt, neither have ye brought again that which hath been driven away, nor bound up that which hath been broken, nor healed that which hath been ſick; but with force and cruelty do ye rule, ſpeaking peace to them that put into your mouths, and they that do not, againſt them ye prepare War, to wit, go to law, and take away their Good by force; ye are thoſe that are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing the Viſion, (<hi>Dan.</hi> 11.14.) robbing the people, and exalting your ſelves; but at the time appointed ye ſhall fall, and never riſe again: the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it, but firſt ye will do wickedly, and by reaſon of them that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the holy Covenant, Woe unto them; by you and your deceit, and flattery will the holy people deeply ſuffer, and by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116559:14"/>the reſt of your Sects; and the abomination that maketh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation will yet be exalted. Woe unto you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I am the light of the world,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>that lighteth every man that cometh into the world,</hi> and that Chriſt ſaid, <hi>They ſhall hale you out of their Synagogues, and ye, ſhall be brought before Magiſtrates, and Rulers for my names ſake, and they ſhall ſcourge you, and caſt you into priſon, and ye ſhall have tribulation ten dayes, that ye may be tryed; he that endures to the and ſtall be ſaved, and ſhall have a Crown of glory. And if they kill you (mark) they ſhrit think they do God good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</hi> This is fulfilling by you Prieſts, in particular by you <hi>George Long,</hi> and Prieſt <hi>Sangers</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> for by your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry (cauſing) have I been haled out of the Synagogue, and caſt into priſon, and haled before Magiſtrates. And,</p>
                  <p>Moreover, thou <hi>George, Long,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouldeſt have the blood of me, and my innocent Friends, to quen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h thy blood thirſty mind, for thou ſaidſt (near the 23 day of the 5 month laſt, in <hi>Iohn Biggs</hi> houſe (where ye Prieſts and Magiſtrates were feaſting and feeding without the fear of the Lord) thou wouldeſt have three or four Quakers hanged for an example; <hi>William Ruſſel</hi> asked thee wherefore, but thou couldſt give no juſt account, now let all that fear the Lord judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou art not a murtherer, and blood-thirſty hater of the upright, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29. And <hi>as troops of robbers wait in the way for a man, ſo the company of Prieſts murther by conſent,</hi> and <hi>no murtherer hath eternal life abiding in him.</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.15. <hi>and when ye ſpread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you,</hi> ſaith the Lord God; <hi>and though ye make many prayers, I will not hear you, for your hand are full of blood, Iſa.</hi> 1.15. The Lord is againſt you, and will not appear among you, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be in his fierce wrath and indignation. The light of Chriſt in you ſhall witneſs this to be truth, of which thou <hi>George Long</hi> ſcornfully asked if it were the light of a candle we ſpake of to be within us; to which thus ſaith the Lord God, That in the day thou ſhalt run to hide thy ſelf in thy ſecret chamber of imaginary and vain hope, in which thou haſt conſulted with the lying ſpirits of Divination, and Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, and I, that am the dreadful God, there meet thee (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thou Repent) with my ſpirit of wrath and indignation,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116559:14"/>even in burning flames of fire; then ſhall the ſcorner be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, and then thou ſhalt confeſs that I am not a natural light, ſaith the Lord God.</p>
                  <p>And when thou <hi>George Long</hi> wenteſt to the houſe of <hi>T. C.</hi> to demand hire of him which never ſet thee a work, nor made any condition with thee, neither will he buy thy Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byloniſh ſtuff, but did (to thy face) deny thee to be a Miniſter of Chriſt, neither doſt thou abide in his Doctrine, but are a Swearer, and forcer of others ſo to do (contrary to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, and his Miniſters, who ſay, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> by any Oath, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. <hi>James</hi> 5.12.) Witneſs to this the men of <hi>Witcombes</hi> Pariſh, whom thou compelledſt to ſwear: and at that time when thou waſt at <hi>T.C.</hi> his houſe, and his Wife charged thee for thy lye, and falſe report againſt the innocent, thou badſt her and the reſt (if it were a lye) take it, and make ſport with it.</p>
                  <p>Now all people that love your Souls, take notice of <hi>George Long</hi> who is a reporter of lyes, and bids others take them, and make ſport with them: ſo he doth plainly manifeſt himſelf to be one of thoſe falſe Prophets that Chriſt ſaid ſhould come in the laſt dayes, of whom ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Ye ſhall know them by their fruits, Mat.</hi> 7.20. And theſe are the fruits of the falſe Prophets, to wit, ſporting themſelves with their own deceivings; (mark ye that are makers of Feaſts with your Prieſts) while they feaſt with you, having eyes full of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and that cannot ceaſe from ſin, (take notice) beguiling unſtable ſouls; an heart they have, exerciſed with covetous practiſes, (mark) curſed children, which have forſaken the right way of the Lord, and are gone aſtray, following the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> who loved gifts and rewards (as ye Prieſts do) the wages of unrighteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. from verſe 1. to 15, from the 10 Verſe of <hi>Jude,</hi> to the 19. And in thoſe two Chapters ye may read a true diſcovery of the Prieſt, and falſe Prophets.</p>
                  <p>And thou <hi>George Long</hi> ſaidſt (at the time aforeſaid) to <hi>T.C.</hi> that the <hi>Quakers</hi> preach the Doctrine of the Pope, to wit, <hi>Perfection.</hi> Now whether the Doctrine of <hi>Perfection</hi> be a Doctrine of the Pope, or falſe, let the light of Chriſt in all judge; for the bleſſed God, his ſervants, and Prophets
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116559:15"/>and Chriſt Jeſus and his Miniſters preached the Doctrine of <hi>Perfection,</hi> the Lord ſaid to <hi>Abraham, Walk before me, and be thou perfect, Gen.</hi> 17.1. And <hi>Moſes</hi> (his ſervant) preached perfection, and ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt be perfect with the Lord thy God,</hi> and not follow them that uſe Divination, &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.11, 12, 13. <hi>David</hi> preached <hi>Perfection,</hi> 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 28.9. and ſaid, <hi>Know thou the God of thy Fathers, and ſerve him with a perfect heart. Hezekiah</hi> did witneſs he had walked before the Lord in truth, and with a <hi>perfect heart,</hi> and had done that which was good in his ſight, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.3. And <hi>Solomon</hi> preached <hi>Perfection,</hi> and ſaid, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.61. <hi>Let your heart be perfect with the Lord our God, to walk in his Statutes, and keep his Commandements;</hi> and <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.5. <hi>The righteouſneſs of the perfect ſhall direct his way,</hi> (mark George Long) <hi>but the wicked ſhall fall by his own wickedneſs.</hi> And <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> (that holy Prophet) preached <hi>Perfection,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Thou wilt keep them in perfect peace, whoſe minds are ſtaid on thee,</hi> Iſai. 26 3, 4. And the Lord Jeſus (the everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of God) preached <hi>Perfection,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Be ye perfect, even as your Heavenly Father is perfect, Mat.</hi> 5.48. And <hi>Paul</hi> (his Miniſter) preached <hi>Perfection,</hi> not with enticing words of mans wiſdom, but in the demonſtration, power, and Spirit of the Lord: howbeit, he preached wiſdom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them (mark) that were perfect; and therein did <hi>Paul</hi> ſtrive and labour according to the mighty workings of the Lord in him, (mark) to preſent every man perfect in Chriſt Jeſus; and therefore having theſe promiſes, ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> (ſee what the promiſes were, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.3 laſt verſes) <hi>Let us cleanſe our ſelves,</hi> (take notice ye that ſay, that man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be free from ſin on earth) <hi>from all filthineſs of fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſh and ſpirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of the Lord;</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>they were, not come to the Mount that might be touched, but ye are come unto Mnunt Syon,</hi> and <hi>unto the City of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, Heavenly Ieruſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m, and to an innumerable compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Angels, to the general aſſembly, and Church of the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born which are written in Heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect.</hi> And <hi>Epaphras</hi> a ſervant of Chriſt, laboured fervently in prayers, that they might ſtand perfect and compleat; Read theſe Scriptures,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116559:15"/>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4, 5, 6. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.18. to 23. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. <hi>John</hi> 17.23. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.12, 17, 18.</p>
                  <p>Now let all that fear the Lord judge, whether the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Perfection be a Doctrine of the Pope, yea or nay; or whether <hi>G. Long</hi> which denies the Doctrine of Perfection doth not deny the Doctrine of Chriſt, and ſo is an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, 2 <hi>Iohn</hi> 9. and tells the people they cannot be freed from ſin while they are on earth, and yet ſaith, if they have Faith to believe that Chriſt dyed for their ſins, they ſhall be ſaved, and ſo applies the Promiſes to that nature, which the judgements of the Lord are to, preaching peace to the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to whom God hath ſaid, <hi>There is no peace;</hi> and (to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this Doctrine of imperfection) tells people, that <hi>Paul</hi> was a ſinner, and <hi>David</hi> was a ſinner, and that <hi>Iob</hi> was not a perfect man; witneſs to this againſt thee <hi>George Long Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Stokes</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> to whom thou ſaidſt (when I ſent by him to thee a few Queries, which thou never yet anſweredſt, which I ſhall ſend (ſome of them) once more (with ſome others) unto thee, and Prieſt <hi>Sangers;</hi> at that time thou ſaidſt, <hi>Iob</hi> was not a perfect man, and ſo thou blaſphemouſly chargedſt God to be a lyar, which ſaid, Satan, <hi>haſt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered my ſervant Iob? that there is none like him in the earth, a perfect man, one that feareth God, and eſcheweth evill? Iob</hi> 1.8. Therefore thou <hi>George Long</hi> haſt ſpoken wickedly againſt God, Thou thinkeſt that he is altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelf, but he is a pure and holy God, and hath reproved thee, through me the leaſt of his ſervants, and <hi>ſet thy ſins in order before thee,</hi> (as <hi>Pſalm</hi> 50.21.) for although <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid in the anguiſh and bitterneſs of his ſoul and ſpirit that (mark) <hi>if I ſhould juſt fie my ſelf, my own mouth would condemn me; if I ſay I am perfect, it would prove me perverſe;</hi> yet the Lord ſaid, <hi>Iob was a perfect man,</hi> and the Word of the Lord is true; <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid, he was as one deſperate, and did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs his words to be as wind, <hi>ch.</hi> 6.26 for he was not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to fetch his breath by reaſon of the anguiſh and bitterneſs of his Soul, and he deſired the Lord to take his hand and dread off him. And in all this <hi>Iob</hi> ſinned not with his lips, <hi>Iob</hi> 2.10. And <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid, <hi>My face is foul with weeping, and on my eye-lids is the ſhadow of death,</hi> (mark) not <hi>for any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116559:16"/>in mine hands, for all my prayers are pure;</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>My Righteouſneſs I hold faſt, and will not let go, my heart ſhall not reproach me ſo long as I live:</hi> here <hi>Iob</hi> did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs his perfect holy life, <hi>Job</hi> 16.16. and 27.6. And the Lord ſaid again, chap. 2. <hi>Satan, haſt thou conſidered my ſervant Job? that there is none like him in all the earth, &amp;c.</hi> and ſtill he hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth faſt his integrity, <hi>although thou haſt moved me againſt him to deſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> him</hi> (mark) <hi>without a cauſe. Iob</hi> was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man, <hi>and none ſpake of me the things that were right, like my ſervant Job,</hi> ſaith the Lord God Almighty, <hi>Iob</hi> 42.7. And therefore thou <hi>George Long</hi> art a forger of lyes, who ſaidſt, <hi>Iob</hi> was not a perfect man: Thou art a Phyſitian of no value, and the wrath of God is kindled againſt thee, (and all you wicked ones) who are ſearching for the ſin and failings of the holy Fathers of old, thereby thinking to keep people in ſin for terme of life, and alſo to hold up the horrible filthy thing in the Land, and the abomination that maketh deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And although <hi>David</hi> was a ſinner, yet when he ſaw his ſin, he repented, and ſate on the ground, and made Sack-cloth his garments, and prayed the Lord to blot out his ſin, and his iniquities, and to create in him a clean heart, and renew a right ſpirit within him, which <hi>David</hi> did witneſs the Lord had done for him, and had delivered him out of all his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſaid, <hi>I will praiſe the Lord for ever,</hi> (mark) <hi>becauſe he hath done it, &amp;c. Pſ.</hi> 51.9, 10, 52.9.54.7.</p>
                  <p>And although <hi>Paul</hi> did cry out, <hi>O wretched man that I am, &amp;c.</hi> yet he did after witneſs, and ſay, the law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus had made him free from the law of ſin and death, and over death he did triumph, and thanked God that he had given him the victory over his ſin, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.25. and 8.1, 2, 37. and <hi>ch.</hi> 6.16, 17, 18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55. to the end.</p>
                  <p>[This may ſerve to ſatisfie the ſimple, and for a witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee <hi>Rob. Hill,</hi> who falſely reportedſt that I ſaid, <hi>Paul</hi> was not a Saint, or born of God, when he ſaid, <hi>O wretched man, &amp;c.</hi> Thou askedſt me, whether he was not a ſinner? I anſwered, that he that was born of God, did not commit ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But thou by thy conſequences concludeſt, and falſely
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116559:16"/>reportedſt as aforeſaid: Let the wiſe in God judge, to whom I refer my ſelf; I had been ſilent herein (knowing it is honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to ceaſe from ſtrife) had I not been told of it by ſeveral people ſince I came into priſon, for it is near two years ago that the words were ſpoken]</p>
                  <p>Now let all the wiſe in heart judge whether or no <hi>Iob, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> did not witneſs a cleanſing from their ſins and iniquities, and witneſs a perfect holy life, or perfection, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that Doctrine of <hi>George Long,</hi> and others, who quote them for examples to people, that they may live in ſin for terme of life, which is juſt the Doctrine of the Pope, (who in his ground differeth little from the Prieſts of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> though in ſome particular circumſtances they may: for the Pope, and his Jeſuits, and Fryars, tell the people they cannot be free from ſin, or perfect, whiles they are on earth, but tell them there is a Purgatory, where they muſt be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed after death, for which many of them do give their whole eſtates to the Pope, his Fryars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to pray for their Souls after death, that they may be freed of out Purgatory (which they ſay is a place of torment) and go to Heaven. And hence it is through their ſubtilty and craft they have gotten ſo many Abbies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and other yearly Revenues as they have, part of which is now become their Succeſſors, (to wit, the Prieſts of <hi>England;</hi>) and hence was the ground, (to wit, from the Pope) of Glebes, and Tythes, for which the Prieſts of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> contend ſo earneſtly, and ſue men at Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Pope, his Jeſuits, and Fryars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſay, the Wafer or bread is <hi>(Corpus Dei)</hi> the Body of God, and the Wine his Blood, after they have conſecrated it (as they call it,) and ſome of the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> ſay the ſame; and the Pope and his Prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> waſh, or ſprinkle little Children, and call that Baptiſm; and they uſe a form of words at their Graves, bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their dead; and they ſtand praying in the Synagogues and Pulpits, and preach from a Chapter and Verſe, and have Parſonage-houſes, Gleabs, and Tythes, and ſome of them preach for hire, moneys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which the Prieſts of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for the greateſt part of them do the like; and againſt ſuch dumb greedy Doggs who could never have enough, but preach for their gain from their Quarters; the Lord ſent <hi>Iſaiah</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:116559:17"/>to cry, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.10, 11. and againſt ſuch the Lord ſent <hi>Jerimiah</hi> to cry, which did commit the horrible thing in the Land, the Prophets prophecying falſely, and the Prieſts bearing rule by their means, and the people did love to have it ſo, as ye people of <hi>England</hi> do; but what will ye do in the end thereof? ye ſhall lye down in ſorrow, <hi>Iſa</hi> 5.30, 31. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.11. and againſt ſuch the Lord ſent <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> to cry, who did make a prey of the prople, and deſtroyed Souls for diſhoneſt gain, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.3, 4. and 27.4. And againſt ſuch the Lord ſent <hi>Micah</hi> to cry, which did preach for hire, and divine for money, as your Prieſts and Divines do, <hi>Micah</hi> 3.10, 11. And Chriſt ſaid, ye ſhall <hi>know them by they fruits;</hi> and againſt ſuch Chriſt Jeſus cryed, who ſtood pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Synagogues, and were called of men Maſter, and had the chief Seats in the Aſſemblies, and the uppermoſt rooms at Feaſts, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.6, 7.</p>
                  <p>Now all people who have been learning the way of truth from your prieſts, ſome 20, 30, 40 years, ſome more, ſome leſs, and have given them great Gifts and Rewards, and yet ye are as ignorant of the true way to eternal life, as ye were the firſt time you went to hear them: and look with a ſingle eye on your Prieſts, and ſee what difference there is between their Doctrine, and that of the Popes.</p>
                  <p>Therefore be ye warned of them all people, before the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible day of the Lord come upon you, and conſume you as ſtubble, for in that day the wicked ſhall be as ſtubble, which is come, and coming, and with the Rod of his mouth will he ſmite the earth, and with the breath of his lips will he ſlay the wicked; therefore while ye have time, prize it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, for though there be a righteous holy life to be attained through Chriſt Jeſus,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 4.4.</note> whoſe blood cleanſeth from all ſin; yet thoſe whom he doth redeem by his Spirit of burnings, and of judgement from ſin,
<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.6.</note> he doth redeem them henceforth not to live in ſin, but unto him which dyed and roſe again (he that hath an ear to hear,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.15.</note> can hear) to ſerve him (mark) in newneſs of life; and if ever any of you come to witneſs a perfect holy life, either Prieſt, or People in any meaſure; ye muſt come to witneſs a real, not feigned, forſaking of your evil wayes, and a daily dying and crucifying of that life that now liveth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116559:17"/>in you, with all its luſts and affections;
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.24.25, 16. Rom 6.4.</note> And the life that ye have ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne (whiles ye have nouriſhed your hearts as in the day of ſlaughter) to be raiſed by the power and glory of the Lord God, even as Jeſus was raiſed from the dead, &amp;c. And therefore your ſaying, <hi>ye hope ye ſhall be ſaved from your ſins, and ye believe Chriſt dyed for your ſins, and by faith in Chriſt, ye ſhall be ſaved, &amp;c.</hi> It is not your ſpeaking thoſe words, and living in ſin, will ſerve your turns, for Chriſt is come and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to give to every one, according as their works ſhall be: And therefore that beliefe, that doth not lead you out of ſin and evil, and to live a truly righteous holy life, it is the belief of Devils, for, <hi>the Devils believe and tremble, Iam.</hi> 2.19. Therefore ſaith Chriſt, <hi>who is the light of the world,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.12. Ioh. 12.46.</note> that light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every one that cometh into the world; that whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth,</hi> (mark and underſtand aright) <hi>and followeth, ſhall not abide in darkneſs, but ſhall have the light of life; God is light and in him is no darkneſs: If ye ſay ye believe in the light, and walk in darkneſs,</hi> ſin and evil, <hi>ye are lyers and the truth is not in you,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.5, 6.
<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.3.</note> And that hope that is not <hi>purifying your hearts, even as he is pure,</hi> is the hope of the hypocrite, <hi>and the hope of the hypocrite ſhall periſh:</hi> And that faith which doth not give you victory over ſin, and the world,
<note place="margin">Ia. 2.10.26</note> (which is in your hearts, out of which proceedeth evil thoughts, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries murders, thefts, covetouſneſs, pride, deceit, and all manner of wicked uncleanneſs) that faith is a dead faith, <hi>for whatſoever is born of God, overcomes the world, and that is your victory over the world, even your faith,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.4.</p>
                  <p>Now in the light of Chriſt in you all, Judge whether ye have this true hope, faith and belief, with their effects and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations, as they are in Jeſus; ye or nay? For though <hi>Moſes</hi> did tell the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of a land of reſt, which was truth, yet after the Lord by his power, delivered them from the oppreſſions of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and his Task-maſters, and brought them through the Sea, &amp; delivered them from their enemies that purſued them, and from many other enemies in their travels, and lead them through Wilderneſſes, and through a great and terrible Wilderneſs, wherein were Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, and fiery Serpents, &amp; drought &amp; no water; <hi>Deut</hi> 8.15. Yet I ſay, many for their rebellion, diſobedience and hardneſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116559:18"/>of heart, and unbelief, entred not into that land of reſt, but dyed in the Wilderneſs, but the faithful and obedient, did enter into the land of promiſe; I have transferred this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you as a figure, if ye can receive it, do. Now all theſe things happened unto them for examples, And they are written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come.</p>
                  <div type="queries">
                     <p>Theſe following are the <hi>Queries</hi> I ſend to you, <hi>Georg Long,</hi> and <hi>Prieſt Sangers</hi> of <hi>London;</hi> which I do require you to anſwer; by plain Scripture, which if ye do, the falſe Prophets and Anti-chriſts, and Deceivers, will be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, and the truth cleared from ſalſhood.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 1. Whether ever any of Chriſts Miniſters were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors, or caſters into priſon, for ſpeaking in their Church; it being their order and manner that if any thing was reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him that ſtood by, the firſt ſhould hold his peace, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.30.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 2. Whether ever any Miniſter of Chriſt, did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in one place, ſeven or eight years, or their life time, in a parſonage houſe, or preach for 40. 50. 60. or 100. or more, or leſs, by the year; yea or nay, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 3. Whether Chriſts Miniſtry be not now the ſame as ever, both for matter, manner, and Maintenance? If ye ſay nay, prove when it was changed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.8.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 4. Whether it were not the chief Prieſts, with <hi>Pilate</hi> and the reſt that killed Ieſus, hanged him on a tree, and wrote letters of Greek and Hebrew, over his head, which ye call your Original tongues? And whether they did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs themſelves to be <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, and <hi>Moſes</hi> diſciples, and as ſeemingly zealous as ye prieſts of <hi>England</hi> do, who are crucifying of him a freſh, perſecuting and killing his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, under pretence of blaſpheming, as your fathers did the juſt one aforſaid? anſwer this <hi>Querie</hi> in plainneſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.56.57. <hi>Luke</hi> 23.38.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 5. Whether Chriſt be not the light of the world, and lighteth every one that cometh into the world? And whether that light that lighteth every one that cometh into the world, be not ſafficient to lead unto eternal Salvation, all
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116559:18"/>that believe and follow it? <hi>John</hi> 8.12. <hi>Iſa</hi> 46.7. <hi>Heb</hi> 5.8, 9.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 6. What is the firſt principle of true Chriſtian Religion?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 7. What and where is that key of knowledg, which being taken away, the kingdome of God is ſhut from men? And how did the blind Guids take away the key of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg? <hi>Luke</hi> 11.52.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 8. What is that that checketh for ſin and evil in the conſcience, if it be not the light of Chriſt, ſeeing that man by nature is the child of wrath, and at enmity againſt God, in him dwels no good thing; But that is good in man, though not of man, that ſhews the evil in man, and that is light that ſhews the darkneſs, therefore not natural; nor of nature, <hi>Eph</hi> 5.13. ch. 2. 3. <hi>Rom</hi> 7.18. and ch. 8.7.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 9. What is the one Baptiſme, and how may one know he is baptized into that one baptiſme? <hi>Eph</hi> 4.5.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 10. Whether ever Chriſt Jeſus or his Miniſters, did waſh or ſprinkle little children, calling it Baptiſme? Or whether ever they did uſe that <hi>Popiſh</hi> form, ſpeaking the words of <hi>Iob</hi> or any other Scripture at the grave? Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt or his miniſters did ſing <hi>Davids prayers,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies, in meetre, yea or nay?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 11. What and where is that everlaſting covenant, the Lord ſaid he would make with his people? And what is the ſeal of the Covenant? And what is that annointing, of which <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid to the Church, ye have received of him, and abides in you, and ye need not that any man teach you, <hi>Ier</hi> 32.40. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.27.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 12. Seeing the Scriptures ſay, <hi>ye ſhall be all taught of God;</hi> Whether any may expect it in theſe dayes? And whether the teachings of God in ſpirit, by his eternal ſpirit, and by his law written in the inward parts, be not ſufficient to lead unto everlaſting life or ſalvation, to all that believe and follow it, without your teachings from your ſenſual wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which is from beneath, ye, or nay?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 13. Whether they are not falſe Prophets Deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and of the Devil, who through covetouſneſs make mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of the people; And are crying, ſo here is Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> there he is, and by feigned words, and fine ſpeches,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116559:19"/>deceive the hearts of the ſimple, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 21.2.3. <hi>Rom,</hi> 16.18.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 14. What is the croſs of Chriſt, &amp; what is it a Croſs to? And whether ye are not enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt, whoſe God is your belly, whoſe glory is your ſhame, and who mind earthly things? <hi>Phil</hi> 3.18.19.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 15. What is it in man that ye miniſter unto? And from what do ye minſter?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 16. Whether the Scriptures, the declaration of the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, be that living word of God, that liveth and abideth for ever? 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.23.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 17. What and where is that way of holineſs, which the unclean ſhall not paſs over, but it ſhall be for thoſe, the wafering men, who (though fools) ſhall not err there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, no ravenous Beaſts, Lyons whelps or fierce Lyon hath trod it, or paſſed by it, no fool knoweth it, nor the vulturous eye hath not ſeen it? <hi>Iſa</hi> 35.8, 9. <hi>Iob</hi> 28.6, 7.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 18. What is the firſt reſurrection; And whether ye can witneſs ye are partakers of the firſt reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 19. What and where is the tree of life? and what is the flaming ſword, that turneth every way, to keep the tree of life, <hi>Gen</hi> 2.9. and 3.24.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Querie</hi> 20. Whether ye have an infallible Spirit to Iudge and try all Spirits? And where is that Spirit of truth, which Chriſt ſaid he would ſend, that ſhould guide into all truth, and ſhew things to come, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.13.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="continuation_of_text">
                     <p>I have here propoſed Scriptures, Chapters, and verſes, to theſe <hi>Queries.</hi> Becauſe I ſent ſome of them to a Prieſt, by him to be anſwered; and his anſwer was, <hi>that they were not Fundamental;</hi> And therfore for the ſake of the ſimple heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (But not to fatisfie the luſt of any) that they may ſee the deceit and ignorance of their Prieſt, (who are ignorant of the Scriptures) And alſo that ye may ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I have here propoſed them to you in publique.</p>
                     <p>The Lord, that ſearcheth all hearts, knows that I have no envy againſt the perſons of you, <hi>George Long,</hi> and Prieſt <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> or the <hi>Rulers</hi> of <hi>Bath,</hi> or any other by whom I have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, neither would I hurt the leaſt members of your bodies, if
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116559:19"/>I might; And I deſire the Lord not to lay it to your charge, in his dreadful day, wherin ye muſt give an account (to him, with whom ye muſt have to do, will ye nill ye) for every idle word &amp; all the actions done in the body; And I was as great a lover and follower of your Prieſts, as ſome of ye are now; But now the Lord having ſhewed me their deceit and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, that maketh deſolation,
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.15 Iſa 62.1. 1 Ioh. 2.27.</note> ſpoken of by <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet; At it my ſoul is vexed, and for <hi>Sions</hi> ſake I cannot hold my peace till its righteouſneſs ſhine forth in its bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and its ſalvation as a Lamp that burneth. He that hath an ear to hear, can hear and underſtand.</p>
                     <p>And therefore I do charge and require you Prieſts, <hi>George Long,</hi> and <hi>Prieſt Sangers,</hi> in the preſence of the dreadful Lord God, to anſwer theſe <hi>Queries</hi> by plain Scripture, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving meanings or conſequences, or imaginations, hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in your carnal dark minds, <hi>for the Scripture is of no pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate interpretation, neither came they by the will of man, but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men of God ſpake them forth, as they were moved of the holy Ghoſt, and</hi> curſed is he that addeth to them, or diminiſheth from them.</p>
                     <p>Which if ye refuſe to do, you will plainly manifeſt your ſelves to be no Miniſters of Chriſt (for they are no more then what every Miniſter of Chriſt ought to know, and to have the work of them wrought in himſelf, &amp; to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof, and of the hope that is in him, with meekneſs and fear, being required) but Anti-chriſts, and deceivers, and keepers of the people in ignorace and blindneſs, and ye will bring their blood upon your own heads; And ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye ſpeedily repent, the day will come upon you, wherein you will wiſh ye had never been born, then you will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber me, whom the Lord ſent you to forewarn of thoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and indignations that will come upon you, except ye repent, for which meſſage I have been impriſoned neer twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty moneths; where I wait in patience, on the Lord, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, in his time; Let the light of Chriſt, in all that fear the Lord, Judge, whether theſe be the fruits of the Miniſters of Chriſt, or not.</p>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:116559:20"/>
                     <p>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.19.</bibl> 
                           <hi>And the Beaſt was taken, and with him, the falſe Prophet, that wrought miracles before him, &amp;c. Theſe both were caſt alive into a lake, burning with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone; Becauſe when I called, ye refuſed: I have ſtreched out my hand, and no man regarded: But ye have ſet at nought, all my Counſel and would none of my reproof. I alſo will laugh at your calamity, I will mock when your fear cometh, and in your heat I will make your feaſts, and ye ſhall drink, and be drunken, and rejoyce, and ſleep a parpetual ſleep, and not awake; Saith the Lord God of Hoaſts.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>T. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:116559:20"/>
                  <head>A TESTIMONY Againſt the Worlds feigned Love, and Salutations, and flattering Titles.</head>
                  <head type="sub">As alſo againſt their falſe Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, againſt them ſcornfully called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> touching Magiſtracy, Miniſtry, Scriptures, Heaven, and Hell.</head>
                  <head type="sub">And likewiſe againſt the Prayers, and Songs of their Idol Temples, wherein is a true Diſcovery of their eternal Deſtruction, except they repent.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>he world hath a love, and loves its own; And have ſeveral ſalutations and flattering titles, giving to each (as they think) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his or their place, or eſtate, or riches: ſome ſaying, How d'ee, or I am glad to ſee you well; others good morrow, with a put off of the hat, &amp;c. And others with bowings and cringing, ſaying, your humble Servant Sir, or, your ſervants ſervant, &amp;c. And all is but feigned love, and words pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from a deceitful heart, for, when poverty, tribulations, or any other afflictions come, your love, and feigned reſpect have an end. Yet for faſhion-ſake (which will paſs away and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:116559:21"/>have an end alſo) if ye meet each other, ye will ſtill uſe your deceitful ſalutations, (to wit) How d'ee, or I am glad to ſee you well, &amp;c. When ſometimes if ye could avoid it, ye would not ſee each other, and alſo have ſecret envy in your hearts one towards another, and would do any evil one to another, in body or goods, if it were not for ſome ſlaviſh fears, that do poſſeſs you of the law; and ye do backbite, and revile each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, behind one anothers backs, and yet, (if ye do meet each other, if envy and malice be not ſo great in you, that it ſtops your mouths) ye will ſay, How d'ee? I am glad to ſee you well, &amp;c. when ye are not well in body or ſoul, (for envie deſtroys and conſumes body and ſoul) And where there is envie ſtrife and diviſion, there is every evil work, and that is not well,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.16. And ye that ſay, I am glad to ſee you well, &amp;c. know ſometimes that the perſon or perſons to whom ye ſpeak, are not well, but want both food and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ye ſome of you have it in great abundance, albeit ye give them not thoſe things that are needful, and what good do your words do them? Read <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.14.15.16. and 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.17. But as for your ſouls food, healer, or covering, ye are little ſenſible of it (any of you whoſe hearts dwel in the earth) what it is, or where it is. But did ye love and follow the light of Chriſt in you, that checks you for ſin and deceit, and that ſhews you the hypocriſie of your hearts (as is afore ſhewed unto you) it would give you power againſt it, and lead you into the kingdome of God, through the Croſs, where that precious oyntment, covering, and living bread for your ſouls is.</p>
                  <p>And ye that ſay, your humble ſervant Sir; or, your ſervants ſervant, bowing and cringing, uſing many vain words. Are ye not lyers and hypoctites ye, or nay? And is not the woe from God to the hypocrite? And is not the lyer for the lake? when ye ſay, your humble ſervant Sir, &amp;c. Are not your hearts haughty, &amp; puft up in pride, and living in it? And are ye not wanton, ſcornets, mockers, and perſecutors of the innocent? Are theſe the fruits of true humility? Nay, nay, ſee, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23, 24, 25, 26. and there ye ſhall read the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the fruits of true humility, and in the light of Chriſt Judge your ſelves, and ye ſhall not be judged, for ye that uſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116559:21"/>that deceitful ſalutation, ſaying, I am you ſervants ſervant, ye are of <hi>Hams</hi> Generation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.25. And that that is in high eſteem amongſt men, is abomination to the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Therefore repent while ye have time, for the day is come and coming, that an account ſhall be given for every idle word; And by your words (ſaith Chriſt ſhall ye be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, and by your words ſhall ye be condemned, <hi>Math.</hi> 12.36, 27. Therefore all who to the light and life of Chriſt, in any meaſure are come, and by it are guided, cannot uſe your vain words, nor bow to your deceit, not uſe your faſhions (which to them are paſt away) and for that cauſe ye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute them to death, and no murtherer hath eternal life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding in him, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.15.</p>
                  <p>But where do yeread, in all the Scriptures, that any did require any ſuch thing, as putting off the hat, and fining of men, and caſting of them into priſon, if not done? Did ever <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was as a King, a Prieſt and a Prophet to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> who were Kings, ever compel men to ſuch a thing? <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid, my ſon give me the heart, not the hat: Is not the hat an ornament of the body? may ye not as well compel the ſervants of the Lord, to pull off their ſhooes, as their hats? And why do ye compel the male ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the moſt high God, to ſtand bare headed before you more then the Females?</p>
                  <p>Oh! the loftineſs and haughtineſs of man! I will (ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts) ſtain the pride &amp; glory of all fleſh, an woe to the crown of pride: Do ye not ſhew your ſelves to be thoſe whited Sapulchers, which appear very beautiful out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly (or with a ſeeming humility) but are within full of hypocryſie and all uncleanneſs. And although ſome of you, ſay <hi>Abraham, Lot,</hi> &amp;c. bowed, yet they did not bow to the wicked, but it was to the Angels, or Meſſengers of the moſt high God, &amp; although <hi>Jacob</hi> bowed ſeven times, (Bleſſed is he that readeth and underſtandeth) <hi>Jacob</hi> was then in return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his fathers houſe; &amp; thus ſaith the Lord to you, O ye <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites</hi> (or the houſe of <hi>Eſau</hi>) becauſe <hi>Eſau</hi> your father, and ye his children, purſued his brother with the ſword, &amp; did caſt off all pity; and his anger did tear (as yours doth) perpetnal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and he kept (as ye do) his wrath for ever. Therefore
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:116559:22"/>thus ſaith the Lord, the houſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall now be a fire; and the houſe of <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſhall be a flame, and the houſe of <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhall now be for ſtubble, and no one of your fathers houſe ſhall remain, the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it. And to whom then ſhall the ſeed of <hi>Iacob</hi> bow but unto me, ſaith the Lord God of hoſts, whoſe alone right it is?</p>
                  <p>But may I ask you a queſtion, what ſpirit is this that is ſo much contending for honour before men, bowings, putting off the hatt, &amp;c. Is it not that ſpirit that was in <hi>Saul,</hi> when the ſpirit of God was departed from him? Or is it not that that was in <hi>Haman,</hi> that vexed him becauſe <hi>Mordecai</hi> could not bow to him? Or whether it be not that which was in the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> who had prepared an hot fiery furnace, to caſt the Innocents in, becauſe they could not bow to there image? Or is it not that ſpirit that would have had the Lord Jeſus to have bowed, or fallen down and worſhipped him; yea, or nay? which Chriſt reproved and ſaid, <hi>Get thee hence Satan, It is written, thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God,</hi> &amp;c. Mat. 4.10, 11.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, concerning the holy fathers of old, <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Brethren, I would not have you to be ignorant, that all our Fathers were under the cloud, and paſſed through the ſea,</hi> &amp;c. But now, the ſtar of <hi>Jacob</hi> is riſen, the Cloud is ſcattering, the Lord again, as in the ancient of daies, is ſmiting the tongue of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Sea, in the ſeven ſtreams; this is enough to the wiſe.</p>
                  <p>And all that (but) to <hi>Mount Sion</hi> are come, a Law from God, they have received, which ſaith, Thou ſhalt not bow, &amp;c. And the Scripture doth teſtifie, that <hi>Peter</hi> a Miniſter of Chriſt, and his holy Angel, did deny, and forbid bowing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, for when <hi>Cornelius</hi> would have fallen down or bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Peter,</hi> he denyed it, and ſaid, <hi>ſtand up, for I my ſelf alſo am a man,</hi> Acts 10.25, 26. And when the Angel came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>John,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19: 10. 22.9. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20 45. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.8, 9. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9.</note> he fell down, and would haue worſhipped the Angel, But he forbad it, ſaying, <hi>ſee thou do it not,</hi> I am thy fellow-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and of thy brethren the Prophets, which keep the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the book, <hi>worſhip God, which is a ſpirit. And unto me ſaith the Lord God, ſhall every knee bow, both in Heaven, and in earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:116559:22"/>
                  <p>So that it is evident, that there is not one Scripture, that doth require any ſuch thing, as putting off the hat, or bowing; But the Scriptures do teſtifie againſt it, and forbid it, as I have prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before, except it be that of Solomon which ſaith, <hi>The evill ſhall bow before the good, and the wicked at the gate of the righteous,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And although <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſtand up before the hoary head;</hi> yet he did not ſay, they ſhould put off the hat, or bow, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And as for you who are contending for flattering titles of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, which yee ſay, <hi>Paul</hi> gave to <hi>Feſtus, Agrippa,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> to <hi>Theophilus, Iohn</hi> to the Lady, &amp;c. This cover is too narrow for your deceipt, in the light of Chriſt are ye ſeen, judged and deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for, when <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, noble <hi>Feſtus,</hi> &amp;c. and O King <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake as he found by them, for they were more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than the Tumultuous Jewes, who took him (to wit <hi>Paul</hi>) with <hi>Sylas,</hi> and caſt them into the inner Priſon,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 26.22, 23, 24, 25.</note> and made their feet faſt in the ſtocks; And the Magiſtates rent their clothes, and beat them uncondemned, &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 22.25. But when <hi>Paul</hi> came before <hi>Feſtus</hi> and <hi>Agrippa,</hi> they were more noble, than thoſe aforeſaid, &amp; gave him leave peaceably to give an account of his faith, and the hope that was in him; neither were they offended at <hi>Paul,</hi> when he Thee'd and Thou'd them. And they judged him without partiality, and ſaid, <hi>we find nothing worthy of death, or of bonds, in this man,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo they were truly noble in their judgments to <hi>Paul,</hi> and to this <hi>Pauls</hi> words do much accord, for when he came to the <hi>Bereans,</hi> he ſaid, they were more noble than the tumultuous Jewes of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> in that they received the word with already<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind, and ſearched the Scriptures daily, whether theſe things <hi>Paul</hi> teſtified of, were ſo, &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.10, 11. And hence was the true ground of <hi>Pauls</hi> ſaying, Noble <hi>Feſtus,</hi> O King, &amp;c. which was for their noble and true judge ment of <hi>Pauls</hi> inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſency, as is aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>And when <hi>Luke</hi> ſaid, moſt excellent <hi>Theophilus,</hi> &amp;c. It was for his love to the truth of Jeſus, which <hi>Theophilus</hi> was inſtructed in. And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>he accounted all things but dung in compariſon of the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>The righteous is more excellent than his neighbour, but the way of the wicked ſeduceth them.</hi> But ſuch a one was not <hi>Theophilus,</hi> who was inſtructed in the way of God; and therefore <hi>Luke</hi> a ſervant of the Lord Jeſus thought, good to give him a more perfect under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116559:23"/>of all things from the very firſt, in order concerning the Lord Jeſus, &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 1, 1, 2, 3, 4. And hence was it, that <hi>Luke</hi> did account <hi>Theophilus</hi> excellent, or more excellent than <hi>Herod, Pilate,</hi> and the wicked high Prieſts, who ſeduced them to kill the juſt One.</p>
                  <p>And when <hi>John</hi> wrot to the Elect Lady, it was not one who lived in idleneſs, pride, wantonneſs, luſts, exceſſe of ryoting, whoſe appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel was laced with ſilver or gold, or uſed plaiting of the hair, or looked for flattering titles, or reſpect to her perſon. But it was one who was covered with the ornament of a meek and quiet ſpirit, who had her children walking in the truth, whom I love ſaith <hi>Iohn</hi> (mark) in the truth, and not onely I, but alſo all they that have known the truth, which truth, leads out of all the evills, afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, read 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1.2, 3, 4. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 3. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4. for though <hi>John</hi> did not ſpeak thoſe words, yet <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>James</hi> did for the moſt part, &amp; the ſpirit of Chriſt was but one in them, and ye who are called <hi>Ladies, Maddam,</hi> &amp;c. in the light of Chriſt judge your ſelves whether ye have the fruits of the Elect Lady, or whether ye are any of thoſe vertuous women, ſpoken of, <hi>Pro.</hi> 31. who are doing good, not evill, all the dayes of their lives, ſeeking the wool and flax, working willingly with their hands, (not in vain toyes, but) with the ſpindle and diſtaffe; or whether ye are not with ſome of your husbands, who are plotting and wreſting the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the poor and needy, living in all manner of ſin and evill, perſecuting the innocent, yea, or nay, theſe are not the fruits of of true Humility, or Nobility, nay, nay; to the light of Chriſt in all your conſciences I ſpeak.</p>
                  <p>And whereas ſome of you ſay, we hold there is no Heaven nor Hell, but that in the conſcence; ye are falſe accuſers, <hi>for if in this life onely were our hope of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19.</note> we were of all men moſt miſerable,</hi> for they who to the life of Chriſt, by faith in him, in any meaſure, are come, can ſay (with <hi>Paul, that all our preſent ſufferings, are not worthy to be compared with the glory which ſhall be revealed in us, which hath been hid from ages and generations, but now is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in his Saints, Chriſt the hope of glory.</hi> And in love to this glorious life, (we have in meaſure received as the earneſt, for obedience to the faith) of the eternall inheritance, as we abide in it) our deareſt relations of all viſible created objects whatſoever, and our lives alſo, are not dear unto us in compariſon of it. <hi>And
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:116559:23"/>we know that when this our earthly tabernacle ſhall be deſſolved, we have a building with God, not made with hands,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5, 1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> (mark) <hi>eternall in the Heavens, for in this we groan earneſtly,</hi> &amp;c. and they who to this life are come (as I ſaid before) in any meaſure, can witneſs, the great torment and tribulation, they have paſſed thorough, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.22. which is the portion for everlaſting, of the wicked,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſa.</hi> 17.14. <hi>Pſa</hi> 13.5.67.8. <hi>Job</hi> 21.6. to. 15.</note> who have their portion of eaſe, joy, pleaſure, only in this life, and have more than heart can wiſh; <hi>whoſe eyes ſtand out with fatneſs, their houſes are ſafe from fear, neither is the rod of God upon them; their bull gendereth, and faileth not, their Cow calveth,</hi> &amp;c. your children dance &amp; have the Tymbrel &amp; Harp, &amp; rejoyce in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, therefore they &amp; you their parents, ſay unto God, <hi>depart from us, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>to the end,</hi>
                        </note> and what is the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, that we ſhould ſerve him,</hi> &amp;c. And ye ſpend your dayes in wealth, <hi>perſecuting the innocent; but in a moment go down to the grave.</hi> And to ſuch Chriſt is now ſaying, <hi>Depart from me, ye curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> (take notice) <hi>into everlaſting fire,</hi> woe is me for you, ye wicked ones, Repent while ye have time, this is the day of your viſitation, &amp; ſalvation proffered unto you, who are wanton, &amp; in pleaſure on the earth, nouriſhing your hearts as in the day of ſlaughter, ye have condemned and killed the juſt, and he doth not reſiſt you.</p>
                  <p>And as for you who have gone up and down to get men to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to your grievous Preſcription, which ye have preſcribed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the innocent ſaying they (who are called <hi>Quakers</hi>) deny the Sriptures, and are <hi>Jeſuites;</hi> witneſs to this ye of <hi>Marſhfield,</hi> &amp; thereabouts, and others, ſaying, they deny Magiſtrates and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, Government, &amp;c. thereby thinking to cover your wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, that ye have purpoſed againſt the guiltleſs.</p>
                  <p>I who am a Servant of the living God, and a fellow feeler and partaker of their ſufferings, am moved of the Lord, to ſend forth this as a witneſs againſt you, who have done, and are doing ſo wickedly, for ſo we who are ſcornfully called <hi>Quakers,</hi> hated and perſecuted without a cauſe, do own Magiſtrates and good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, whether the King as ſupream, or any other Governors, who are of the Lord, ſent for the puniſhment of evill doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well, for ſo is the will of God, &amp;c. for no Magiſtrate ought to be a terror to good and godly men or any other good thing; But if he be, he bears the ſword in vain, &amp; the ſword ſo the Lord, will be turned againſt him, and cut him off,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:116559:24"/>as were <hi>Ahab, Jehoaſh.</hi> and others, as the Scripture teſtifies, that did oppreſſe his people: nay, look to our dayes, remember <hi>Wentworth</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp; the late King, with other of that generation. Take notice, ye that are in authority are ye better than they? Nay, ye are not, if ye walk in their ſteps, and ye will have their end, except ye repent. And as for you who are in Authority, and act contrary to the pure law of God, which ought to be your rule, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.18.19. and are acted by your wills and luſts, and unrighteous Laws, wereby we ſuffer deeply; yet to you alſo are we ſubject, in that we ſuffer under your great oppreſſion, without reſiſting of you, which we rather chuſe to doe, than to diſobey the royall Law ſtatutes and judgements of the moſt high and holy God.</p>
                  <p>And Miniſters of Chriſt we own, who abide in the doctrine of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Iohn</hi> 9. But <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> &amp; all that wicked <hi>Popiſh</hi> Generation, we do them deny, for they are as great enimies to the truth, as it is in Jeſus, as the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> are, who abide not in his Doctrine, and will uſe and are uſing, the Servants of the Lord, whom he hath ſent, and is ſending unto them, them to forewarn of the plagues and righteous Judgements of God, that are coming upon them, as bad as your prieſts of <hi>England</hi> have done; who have given, and are giving them a wicked example, and your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward will be a like.</p>
                  <p>And the Scriptures we do own and are ours, and are for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of us, being given by inſpiration of God, and to us they are profitable for Doctrine and reproof, for correction, &amp; inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in righteouſneſs, that thereby we may be thoroughly furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to every good work of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>And therefore all ye who are plotting and perſecuting of the Lords choſen ones, (whom he hath redeemed, and is redeeming, with his pretious blood, and by judgement, <hi>Eph.</hi> 17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.27. out of the worlds cuſtomes, faſhions, words, &amp;c.) fining of them, and caſting them into priſon, for not bowing or putting off the hatt, &amp;c. to ſatisfie your wills and luſts, and ſome of you are afflicting, and whipping, and putting of them into ſtocks, other ſtoning &amp; dirting of them, in ſtreets &amp; high wayes, they not giving you the leaſt offence in word or action; ye are thoſe that rob the Lord of his honour, &amp; haters of <hi>Sion,</hi> &amp; the Lord will plead with you all, poor and rich, by fire and ſword, and will cut your cords of wickedneſs aſunder, and ye will be as graſſe that groweth on
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:116559:24"/>the houſe top, that withereth before it be grown up, wherewith the mower filleth not his hand, nor he that bindeth ſheaves, his boſome, neither will they which paſs by, ſay, we bleſs you in the name of the Lord, or the bleſſing of the Lord be upon you, neither receive you into their houſe, or bid you God ſpeed, for he that ſo doeth, will be partaker of your evil deeds, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 129.4 to the end, 2 <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.11 And then will the prayers and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of <hi>David,</hi> which ye have made the Songs of your Temples, (unto which ye have added and diminiſhed both words and verſes; Witneſs <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. and 15. with many others, therefore denyed by the Children of light) will come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you who are Confederates, perſecuting the innocent, for ye ſing, <hi>your hearts are foul and vain,</hi> and death in haſt will fall on you, and ſend you quick to hell, except ye repent. Will it not be juſt with the Lord to anſwer your prayers, who are doing ſo wickedly, Read and underſtand what ye ſing, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 5.6, 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.16. Are ye not lyars and Hypocrites when ye ſing <hi>All the night I waſh my bed with tears,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>My joynts in ſunder break,</hi> My <hi>heart doth in my body melt, like wax againſt the heat,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>My tongue cleaves to my jawes.</hi> Are not your tonges at liberty, utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth deceit? And are not your hearts as hard as the nether mill-ſtone? And do ye not ſpend the night in ſleep and eaſe? O ye ſimple ones, when will ye be wiſe? Do ye not know the lyar is for the Lake, ye ſing and ſay; <hi>ye do not haunt with men, whoſe deeds are vain, to come into the houſe ye do refuſe with the deceitful train; ye much abhor the wicked ſort:</hi> it were well if ye did, But are ye not ſome of them that are taking Counſel againſt the Lords annointed ones? If ye ſay nay, Then are ye not ſome of them that reſort into the Temples or Synagogues, (called Churches) Into which come all manner of wicked lewd perſons, The light of Chriſt in all your conſciences, ſhall eternally witneſs this to be truth, and anſwer your condemnation to be juſt, except ye ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily repent, &amp; come out from amongſt them, &amp; touch not the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean thing; underſtand what you ſing and read, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26. for the Lord is diſcovering the ſecrets of al hearts, ye read, or ſing, <hi>My wounds ſtink and and are feſtred ſo, as loathſome is to ſee, &amp;c. That ye go wailing all the day in doleful heavyneſs, &amp;c.</hi> And ye ſay or ſing, <hi>ye roare for grief of heart, and are not puft in mind, and have no ſcornful eye,</hi> &amp;c. How dare ye to be ſo preſumptious, to breath
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:116559:25"/>forth ſuch abominable untruths before the Lord, when ye are at eaſe, clothed in rich arayment, perfumed with ſweet ſmells, and are haughty, ſcorners, puft up with pride of mind, living in wantonneſs eaſe, and pleaſure, ſinging vain ſongs and times, having eyes full of adultery, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>By this ye may as in a Looking-glaſſe, ſee and read your figure, and alſo what blindneſs and ignorance your Preiſts have lead you into, that ye are not truly ſenſible, when ye ſing, whether it be for a bleſſing or a curſe, and therefore I was moved, out of tender love to your ſouls, that ye might come to conſider aright, of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to forewarn you of thoſe plagues, that ye ignorantly pray for to come upon you, which will aſſuredly come upon you ſpeedily, except ye repent. The light of Chriſt in all your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſhall eternally witneſs me to be true, and anſwer your condemnation to be juſt, if ye ſleight the day of your viſitation, and ſalvation proffered unto you.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>T. M.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THis Book ſhould have been Printed long ago, but through neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of ſome, and miſtake of others, it hath been prevented a great while; yet now it comes not out of good ſeaſon, but may do its ſervice, to awaken the Witneſs of God, in the Perſecutors of the Righteous Seed, that they may ſee what they have done and repent now, before the laſt plague be, poured out; for the Viols of Gods fury is full, to be poured out upon the head of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, ſo the ſervice of this book, is now in ſeaſon, to anſwer the witneſs of God in all men, to which it is Commended.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
